<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
<!ENTITY appversion "0.3">
<!ENTITY manrevision "0.3">
<!ENTITY date "Sept 2004">
<!ENTITY app "<application>GnuAE</application>">
<!ENTITY appname "GnuAE">
<!ENTITY version "0.3">
]
>

<!-- =============Document Header ============================= -->
<article id="index" lang="en">
  <!-- please do not change the id; for translations, change lang to -->
  <!-- appropriate code -->
  <articleinfo>
    <title>
    &app; Manual V&manrevision;</title>
    <copyright>
      <year>2004</year>
      <holder>Rob Savoye</holder>
    </copyright>
    <!-- translators: uncomment this:
	 
	 <copyright>
	 <year>2004</year>
	 <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
	 </copyright>
	 
    -->
    <!-- An address can be added to the publisher information.  If a role is 
	 not specified, the publisher/author is the same for all versions of the 
	 document.  -->
    <publisher> 
      <publishername> Seneca Software &amp; Solar, Inc.</publishername> 
    </publisher> 
    
    &legal;
    <!-- This file  contains link to license for the documentation (GNU FDL), and 
	 other legal stuff such as "NO WARRANTY" statement. Please do not change 
	 any of this. -->
    
    <authorgroup> 
      <author> 
	<firstname>Rob</firstname> 
	<surname>Savoye</surname> 
	<affiliation> 
	  <address> <email>rob@senecass.com</email> </address> 
	</affiliation> 
      </author> 
      <!-- This is appropriate place for other contributors: translators,
	   maintainers,  etc. Commented out by default.
	   <othercredit role="translator">
	   <firstname>Latin</firstname> 
	   <surname>Translator 1</surname> 
	   <affiliation> 
	   <orgname>Latin Translation Team</orgname> 
	   <address> <email>translator@gnome.org</email> </address> 
	   </affiliation>
	   <contrib>Latin translation</contrib>
	   </othercredit>
      -->
    </authorgroup>
    
    <revhistory>
      <revision> 
	<revnumber>&appname; Manual V&manrevision;</revnumber> 
	<date>&date;</date> 
	<revdescription> 
	  <para role="author">Rob Savoye
	  <email>rob@senecass.com</email>
	  </para>
	  <para role="publisher"> Seneca Software &amp; Solar, Inc.</para>
	</revdescription> 
      </revision> 
    </revhistory> 
    
    <releaseinfo>This manual describes version &appversion; of &appname;.
    </releaseinfo>
  </articleinfo>

  <indexterm zone="index"> 
    <primary>GNUae</primary> 
  </indexterm>

  <!-- ============= Document Body ============================= -->

  <!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->
  <sect1 id="intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    
    <para>
      This is a program that helps one design an NEC compliant
      photovoltaic and wind energy system.
    </para>
    
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/domespread.png" format="png"/>
      </imageobject>
      <caption>
	<ulink type="http" url="http://www.senecass.com/rob/domes">My
	domestead</ulink> in the mountains of Colorado south of
	Rocky Mountain National Park.
      </caption>
    </mediaobject>
    
    <sect2 id="betterintro">
      <title>What is &appname; ?</title>
      
      <para>
	&appname; is a GNOME/GTK compliant GUI for designing
	photovoltaic and wind powered houses with compliance to the
	National Electrical Code. This is important, because you'll
	need to met the code for everything if you get permits, and if
	you decide you aren't getting permits, or don't need one, then
	you still don't want to burn your house down because the
	ampacity was all wrong, or the voltage drop is so huge, you
	barely get any power from your array. Paying attention to the
	NEC code, if if you don't plan to follow it 100% is
	important.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	From personal experience, you want to wire to code. Although
	welding cable makes perfectly fine replacement for the big
	gauge wire the NEC specifies, the same calculations apply. My
	own experience was with my fixer upper geodesic domes. Then
	non-NEC compliant wiring led to the inverter blowing out a
	short time after I bought the house due to poor electrical
	isolation. (the generator shorted out, and took the inverter
	with it) Then we had no AC power till I replaced the
	inverter...(and then later redesigned and rebuilt everything)
      </para>
      
      <para>
	&appname; is designed to make it much easier to wire for NEC code
	compliance without studying all 800 some pages of the NEC
	specification. Even for an electrician, the interdependencies
	between calculations is daunting. While DC wiring is much
	simpler than AC wiring, most household systems are both.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	&appname; currently only runs on Linux, although some attention
	has been paid to eventual ports to MacOSX and M$ WinDoze. This
	is the initial beta release, so your mileage may vary... I'm
	sorry I'm not a GUI programmer, I'm more of a system
	hacker. Please contribute to the development of this project
	by helping track down bugs, or add features. 
      </para>
      
      <para>
	I hope the information contained in this document, along with
	&appname; helps you go off grid, or improve your off-grid life.
      </para>
      
    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>

  <!-- ============= Introduction ============================== -->
  <sect1 id="why">
    <title>Why Use Alternate Energy ?</title>
    
    <para>
      Why should a sane person consider building an off-grid or
      grid-intertie power system ? There are several reasons. To be
      honest, there is no good financial reason to go off grid if you
      have grid power available. In this case grid-intertie makes the
      most sense. But the cost of an alternate energy system, roughly
      $15,000 to $75, takes a long time to pay off compared to grid
      power. The cost of running traditional power lines to property
      can often exceed $50,000 for a short distance.
    </para>

    <para>
      For some of us, we go off grid because there is no grid where we
      want to live. So going off grid is not a financial decision at
      all, it's a lifestyle one. If you want to live in any area far
      from everything else with any convieniences of modern life (like
      light bulbs or a stereo), you need a way to produce your own
      power. There is something really fun about having power, when a
      blizzard has crippled the entire area, and the power is out
      everywhere else for days. (which happens alot in this part of
      Colorado)
    </para>

    <para>
      For those with grid power available, an alternate energy system
      can make your bills go down, which is good in states where power
      is more expensive, like California. I know more than a few
      people than have brought their power bills down to zero, and
      some have made the meter spin backwards. The initial cost may be
      high. but with any tax breaks (like in California), the total
      cost is reasonable.
    </para>

    <para>
      There is also the environmental cost of traditional power
      sources. Nuclear, burning coal or natural gas, or hydro. Other
      than hydro, which does have an impact on the fish in the rivers,
      the other source require environmentally unsound practices. So
      going off grid or grid-interties reduces by that by one little
      household's worth of power the damage needed to have produced
      that power by traditional means. Some people build photovoltaic
      power systems and feed power into the grid gurilla style, just
      to help reduce our dependance on coal or natural gas or nuclear
      power.
    </para>

    <para>
      I also think that it's important for our own personal freedoms
      to break our dependency on the energy monoply. We all benefit
      from being able to make our own choices.
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ============= The Basics ============================== -->
  <sect1 id="basics">
    <title>The Basics of an Alternate Energy System</title>
    
    <para>
      All purely off grid systems have one thing in common,
      batteries. Batteries is where you have the power to use
      electrical devices at night, or after prolonged periods of bad
      weather. Some systems, like water pumping and in some cases
      refridgeration, can run PV Direct, where the panels directly
      power the device without batteries. This doesn't work for
      sources that aer used at night.
    </para>

    <sect2 id="sources">
      <title>Power Sources</title>
      
      <para>
	Currently, there are four main sources for power available to
	the average person. These are hydro, wind, sun,
	generator. Fuel cells are still unattainable to the average
	person in any size big enough to replace a generator.
      </para>

      <sect3 id="hydro">
	<title>Hydro</title>

	<para>
	  Hydro requires a water source with enough drop or enough flow
	  to turn the blades of a generator. A small flow can work with
	  enough drop. I've seen water runs of over a mile sometimes to
	  get enough drop to produce electricity. In our area there are
	  no large enough sources of water. Our Wetlands doesn't have
	  much flow except for a few weeks in the spring, and the bigger
	  creeks, which are too far away to use anyway, freeze pretty
	  solid for over 6 months a year. But if you have it, hydro is
	  the best source for electricity in large volumnes. The
	  downside is if the water goes down. I was visiting at the
	  Breitenbush community last year, and they run multiple
	  houses off of a centralized power system. Because of a
	  drought in Oregon, they didn't have enough electricity, and
	  were running as diesal backup generator 24/7 to keep up.
	</para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="solar">
	<title>Solar</title>

	<para>
	  Sun is a good source of power depending on where you live. To
	  be practical, you need at least 3 hours of clear sun a day on
	  average per week. You can mix sun with other sources for a
	  balanced power system. The advantages to sun power are low
	  maintainance. Once installed, there is nothing to do for about
	  25 years. No moving parts, and other than the glass, nothing
	  to break. And if breaking the glass is a worry, you can buy
	  unbreakable panels. To support photovoltaic panels you'll need
	  some roof space, or you'll need to mount a pole. Pole mounted
	  photovoltaic arrays for any reasonably sized house over 20
	  feet tall aren't practical, but are possible. On average for a
	  roof mounted installation, think something like 20 x 20 feet
	  square. And it has to be south facing, with the possibility of
	  mounting panels at rougly 40-60 degress.
	</para>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/panels.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3 id="wind">
	<title>Wind</title>

	<para>
	  Wind is another source that depends on location. Some areas
	  get constant, or at the best frequent winds. Other areas, like
	  where I live, the long cloudy and stormy periods are usually
	  really windy. So when we're not getting any juice from the
	  photovoltaic panels, the wind kicks in to cover the loss. Wind
	  requires a tower, which can be a pole or a triangular
	  tower. On average, getting 20 feet or more above the tree tops
	  is a good thing. Near the tops of the trees there is more
	  turbulance, which wind generators don't like. One downside
	  with wind is unlike photovoltaics, you just can't turn it off
	  if your batteries are fully charged (like a windy and sunny
	  day). So you need a diversion load to reroute the electricity
	  from the wind generator to something like a water or space
	  heator.
	</para>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/tower.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	
      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="generators">
	<title>Generators</title>
	
	<para>
	  I hate generators. They burn fuel, so they force me into being
	  a consumer for the energy monopoly. They also break, and are
	  noisy and smelly. Long term power production by using
	  generators is expensive, and probably only worth it for small
	  villages that need huge amounts of power. A town near me,
	  Nederland, has recently installed a large 50 Mega Watt wood
	  burning generator, which burns the slash generated from forest
	  fire mitigation projects in the National Forests near
	  here. That was a good idea. But a generator can also be
	  backup power to charge batteries after a long cloudy strech
	  of weather, or used to run occasional heavy loads like we do
	  to pump water from the well into the cistern once a month or
	  so.
	</para>
	<para>
	  A fuel cell is a generator, because it consumes fuel. Many
	  people incorrectly consider a fuel cell a battery. Fuel
	  cells do not store electricity, they make it. Some day a
	  cheap fuel cell that runs the entire house on an inexpensive
	  renewable fuel (hydrogen takes too much power to produce)
	  will be built. Until then, fuel cells are just too expensive
	  to compete with wind and solar.
	</para>
      </sect3>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="generation">
      <title>Power Generation</title>

      <sect3 id="inverters">
	<title>Inverters</title>
	
	<para>
	  Inverters convert DC as stored in your battery bank into AC,
	  so you can run your computer, stereo, or other AC
	  device. Although inverters aren't 100% efficient, they are
	  efficient enough that some people just run only AC devices
	  like my houses.
	</para>
	<para>
	  There are two kinds of inverters, modified sine wave, or
	  true sine-wave. All of the cheap 300 watts inverters you see
	  for cars at truck stops are modified sine wave. A modified
	  sine wave is a squared off and digitally sampled version of
	  a sine wave. A true sine wave is identical to AC power. Some
	  devices don't like the modified sine wave (like stereos or
	  computers), so a true sine wave inverter is recommended.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      
      <sect3 id="dc">
	<title>DC Only</title>

	<para>
	  Even if you have an inverter, it makes sense to use as many DC
	  devices, rather than their AC equivalants for the higher
	  efficiency. Most modern inverters have an idle mode, and an
	  active on mode. On my Trace 4024, this is 16 watts. DC lights
	  work just fine, but unless you have an AC lightbulb
	  that pulls more than 16 watts (many compact flourescents are
	  small than this), the lights will blink. Washers, and other
	  devices that drop below 16 watts occaionally will find them
	  selves with no power at all. One solution is to turn on a
	  light while the washer is running, but you get the idea. DC
	  devices are more efficient and less hassle. Especially if
	  your inverter ever blows out, like happened to me, having
	  most everything DC can be very useful.
	</para>
	<para>
	  I have neighbors whose off-grid houses are purely DC. These
	  are tyically do it yourself types, and their cabins are
	  wired like a car, car batteries, using dome lights, car
	  stereos, etc... The main advantage of these systems is very
	  low cost, and maintainability. I even know of a few folks
	  that have no power generation capability at all, they just
	  charge spare batteries in their vehicles when they make
	  supply runs to the nearest town.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      
    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="storage">
      <title>Power Storage</title>

      <sect3 id="batteries">
	<title>Batteries</title>

	<para>
	  Batteries are a critical part for any off-grid power
	  system. Car batteries just don't cut it... they're designed
	  for an entirely different purpose. If you need to go cheap,
	  golf cart or deep cycle marine batteries will work.
	</para>

	<para>
	  The long-time standard for many off-grid houses for a long
	  time were Trojan L16s. These are about 350AH, and have a
	  lifespan of about 6-8 years. When I bought my domes, they
	  had been running on a set of 12 L16s for about 7 years.
	</para>

	<para>
	  When it came time to replace them, I decided to go with more
	  long lasting batteries so I wouldn't have to do this again
	  in 7-8 years. I went with Surette (Rolls) Batteries this
	  time, even though the ones I bought were 325lbs monsters.

	  <mediaobject>
	    <imageobject>
	      <imagedata fileref="images/rewire04.png" format="png"/>
	    </imageobject>
	    <caption>
	      <para>My friend Greg helps unload batteries in the snow.</para>
	    </caption>
	  </mediaobject>
	</para>

      </sect3>
      
      <sect3 id="pvdirect">
	<title>PV Direct</title>

	<para>
	  Some of the biggest loads in a house can also be run PV
	  direct. This is commonly used to pump water into a cistern
	  for a few hours a day. The advantages of running a water
	  pump directly off the photovoltaics panels is the pump can
	  be powered when it is too far from the battery bank. There
	  are also refridgerators and freezers that can run PV
	  direct.
	</para>

      </sect3>

      <sect3 id="intertie">
	<title>Grid Intertie</title>

	<para>
	  With a grid intertie system one commonly has no
	  batteries. All produced power flows back into the grid, and
	  you also pay for the difference every month between your power
	  consumption and your power production.
	</para>

	<para>
	  It is also possible to build a grid-intertie system with
	  batteries for a backup. The only problem with this approach
	  is that very few inverters are UAL certified to be hooked to
	  the grid, as well as to work with a bank of batteries.
	</para>

      </sect3>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ============= GNUae Application Windows =============== -->
  <sect1 id="window">
    <title>The Windows</title>

    <sect2 id="mainwindow">
      <title>Main Window</title>

      <para>
	The Main window is used to give you an overview of the
	basic power system, namely how many batteries and photovoltaic
	panels are needed. You can also select a few other components
	like inverters and charge contollers to get a rough idea of
	the total system cost. All the values for the quantity of
	photovoltaic panels, batteries, etc... are calculated based on
	the system loads.
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Main GNUae Window</screeninfo>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/MainWindow.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>This is the main window for GnuAE.</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot> 

      <para>
	The only value that get adjusted in this window are the top 4
	rows. The <emphasis>System Nominal Voltage</emphasis> is the
	voltage of the system (the battery bank). This is usually 12 or 24 volts. The
	<emphasis>PV array voltage</emphasis> is the total voltage of
	all the panels wired together. 13, 24, or 48 volts is common,
	with 48 volts for longer runs of wire. <emphasis>Hours of Sun
	per Day</emphasis> is how much sun the array will get
	<emphasis>in the winter</emphasis>. 5 hours is common in much of
	the US. A future feature for &appname; will be adding the
	weatheer charts for the last 30 years. <emphasis>DPV Module is
	of course, which PV module you prefer.</emphasis>
      </para>

      <para>
	<emphasis>The Reserve Time</emphasis> is how many days of no
	sun do you want to have power at your normal level of activity
	? Around here we get these 4-5 day long overcast storms, but
	get by on 3 days reserve because we just conserve power during
	those times. (less loads of laundry) The <emphasis>Usable
	Capacity</emphasis> is how low do you plan to deplete your
	batteries ? 50% is a healthy number, 60% is common.
      </para>

      <para>
	The <emphasis>Temperature </emphasis> is also important. One thing
	that spawned the creation of &appname; was the lack of
	temperature compensation in any of the existing software
	tools. When you live in a cold weather climate, this becomes
	very important as batteries below 41F start to loose alot of
	their efficiency. What this means to you is you have less
	power during cold weather than in warm weather. Around here,
	where my power shed (which is now heated) would get to -35F,
	and especially with my ancient L16s, there was just barely
	enough power to do anything but run light bulbs. Warm weather
	has the same effect.
      </para>

      <para>
	You can also select other system components from the
	menus. The pricing is based on an average price from several
	suppliers circa March 2004. You may find the cost varies from
	this amount, but you get the idea...
      </para>

    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="wiringwindow">
      <title>Wiring Sizes Window</title>

      <para>
	This window details the wiring needed for any alternate
	energy system. This later becomes part of the generated parts
	list. In this caes, all ampacity, overcurrent, and all other
	NEC calculations are done. Any fuzzy issues are resolved
	towards the extra safe side.
      </para>
      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Wiring Window</screeninfo>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/wiring.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>This window displays the sizes of the wires needed.</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot> 

      <para>
	The sizes of your wires is critical to the safety of any power
	system. The current carrying capacity of the wires during
	temperature extremes is very important. Wires run in a conduit
	or other enclosed space get warm, and as the temperature
	rises, the efficiency of the wires goes down, as well as the
	maximum current carrying capacity.
      </para>

      <para>
	Especially with low-power DC systems (12 or 24 VDC), voltage
	loss is also important, and this limits the length of
	wires. All the calculations take into account the possible
	temperatures, as well as current carrying capacity. All the
	data for this is specified in the NEC Code, but spread out over
	a couple of different tables.
      </para>


    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="loadwindow">
      <title>Loads Window</title>

      <para>
	Here is where you choose loads, and how much you use
	them. This is an important part of sizing a systems, as your
	idea of the loads is used for all other calculations. 
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Edit Load Window</screeninfo>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/edit-load.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>This window is for adjusting the system loads.</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot> 

      <para>
	This is where all the values for how much power you will be
	using get entered. All of the power consumption is from my own
	tests with a power meter. Additional database entries will
	always be appreciated.
      </para>

      <para>
	The important data is the amount of time the device will be
	used. Calculations are based on full weeks, since many devices
	aren't used every day. The <emphasis>Watts used per day
	</emphasis> is how much the device will use for the amount of
	time specified. You can also enter in the data, but by
	toggling the <emphasis>Active </emphasis> button, you can turn
	off whether this device is used for calculations or not. This
	is so you can experiment with different configurations.
      </para>

      <para>
	The description isn't used for anything but additional
	information. To add a new load, click the <emphasis>New Load
	</emphasis> button, and then enter the data.
      </para>


    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="necwindow">
      <title>NEC Calculator</title>

      <para>
	The NEC calculator is used to evaluate Voltage Drop
	issues, which are very important in low power DC systems. You
	can also specify the number of condctors.
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>NEC Calculator</screeninfo>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/nec-calc.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>The NEC Calculator</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot> 

    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="chargerwindow">
      <title>Charger browser</title>

      <para>This window lets you browse the database of charge
      controllers. The various features for the controllers is
      displayed, along with the electrical characteristics.
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Colored Rectangles</screeninfo>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/controllers-browser.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>This window displays information on Charge Controllers</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot> 

    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="rpvwindow">
      <title>Photovoltaic Browser</title>

      <para>
	This window displays all the data on photovoltaic panels in
	the database. All the <emphasis>Calculated Values </emphasis>
	currently come from the Sandia National Labs database from
	their testbed, and monitored installations. The original
	motivation for &appname; was to bring these database of real
	performance data back to life. Future releases of &appname;
	will be able to calculate the values from anyone's sensors,
	and add to the database, which does not have any newer
	panels. The data values are used by the main window for
	calculating how many panels are needed.
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Photovoltaic Browser</screeninfo>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/pvbrowser.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>Photovoltaic Browser</phrase> 
	  </textobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>This window display information on PV Panels</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot> 

    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="activewindow">
      <title>Display Active</title>

      <para>
	This window displays the list of active devices, and their
	power consumption. This is so you can view your current
	profile.
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Photovoltaic Browser</screeninfo>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/display-active.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>This window displays information on the active loads</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot> 

    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="invertwindow">
      <title>Inverter Browser</title>

      <para>
	This window displays the database of inverters, and their
	basic features.
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Inverter Browser</screeninfo>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/inverter-browser.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>This window displays information on inverters</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot> 
    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="batterywindow">
      <title>Battery Browser</title>

      <para>
	This window display the database of batteries, and their
	electrical characteristics.
      </para>

      <screenshot>
	<screeninfo>Battery Browser</screeninfo>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/battery-browser.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <caption>
	    <para>This window displays information on batteries</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </screenshot> 
    </sect2> 

  </sect1>

  <!-- ============= Installation Notes ============================== -->
  <sect1 id="notes"> 
    <title>General Notes on Installing</title>

    <sect2 id="wiringnotes">
      <title>Wiring Notes</title>

      <para>
	For wiring photovoltaic panels together, you have a few
	options. The usual NEC compliant way is is to use liquid tight
	conduit and connectors, and run regular wire of the proper
	gauge. You can also use wire rather USE-2/RHW-2, which is
	rated for wet conditions and sunlight. This comes in single
	strands, and runs roughly $0.25/ft. You can also use Tray
	Cable, which commonly has multiple conductors in a
	bundle. This may be more convienient than having lots of
	single wires. These wires need moisture tight connectors. The
	2 conductor Tray Cable needs oval connectors, and the 3
	conductor Tray Cable is round. Because this cable is commonly
	used for AV wiring, it and the round connectors are the
	easiest to find. The 1/2 connectors fit the junction boxes on
	the photovoltaic panel's knockouts.
      </para>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="images/abel-drilling.png" format="png"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>
	Long wire runs between the photovoltaic array and the charge
	controller can be a problem. Voltage drop shouldn't be
	above 3%, and when you are using an MMPT charge controller,
	1.9% is recommended. Long runs of 12VDC are pretty much
	impossible. 24VDC is doable depending on the length, but 48 is
	the most likely. You can get charge controllers like RV
	Products of Outback's MX60 that will handle up to a 60VDC
	source. But big fat wires are difficult to run, especially in
	conduit. In these cases you can run parallel wires, as long as
	they are the same gauge and length.
      </para>


    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="toolsnotes">
      <title>Tool Notes</title>

      <para>
	Me personally, I'm tottally in love with cordless
	tools. Especially when you're working on the roof with ropes
	everywhere, it's nice to not have to screw around with an
	extension cord. My 18V tools have pretty good battery
	life. With two spare batteries I can get through most any day
	of projects. And they have a 12VDC charger, which is nice.
      </para>

      <para>
	I've found the clamp style multimeters have problems in my
	power shed, because they seem to be over sensitive to being
	near the large battery bank. So a regular, and cheaper
	multimeter works just fine. Make sure to get one that does
	DC Amps if possible.
      </para>

      <para>
	I have a power meter, there are several different ones
	available on the market. I use it to test devices before
	buying, as well as testing existing things I can't do
	without. While a power meter is most useful when planning a
	system for sizing purposes, it is also useful for evaluating
	what to buy when looking at AC appliances, like vacumns.
      </para>

    </sect2> 

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="howit"> 
    <title>How It All goes Together</title>

    <sect2 id="howpanels">
      <title>The Panels</title>

      <para>
	Most Photovoltaic panels are wired to support either 12VDC or
	24VDC. A few panels used for PV Direct systems are up to
	110VDC. At one time most PV power systems were wired for
	12VDC, but there are problems with wire size, and sufficient
	voltage for heavy loads. It is entirely possible to have the
	voltage of your PV array be different than your batteries and
	household power.
      </para>	

      <para>
	In my own case, I wired up 4 panels in series at 12VDC apiece,
	to get a 48VDC array voltage. This was so I could run the
	wires from the array to my existing power shed 140 feet away,
	and not use insanely big wires. Big wires are expensive, hard
	to work with, and tough to run through conduit.
      </para>

      <para>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/pvcombiner.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	All the wires from the array go to a PV Combiner box, which
	has fuses and switches in a more convienient place than on the
	roof. From the combiner box, the #10 awg wires are all
	connected using junction blocks, and then it goes to two pairs
	of #2 awg wires that run through conduit to the power shed.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="howwiring">
      <title>The Wiring</title>

      <para>
	The advantages of 12VDC are that many parts are inexpensive,
	and commonly available. Automotive fuses, cigarette lighter
	sockets, lights, can all be adapted. The main disadvantage is
	the voltage drop on long wire runs makes you either keep
	everything near the batteries, or run larger (and more
	expensive) wires.
      </para>

      <para>
	The advantages of 24VDC are that the higher voltage is better
	for heavy loads like refridgerators, water pumps, and light
	bulbs all start faster and run better on 24VDC. You can also
	use commonly available Romex (10 or 12 awg) for most of the
	wiring, and there is less problems due to voltage drop. The
	main disadvantage is that it's much harder to find 24VDC ballasts
	for lights and other components.
      </para>

      <para>
	You really want to pay attention to correctly sizing the
	wires, because burning your house down would be a bad
	thing. Typically for the inverter to battery run, you keep the
	distance short, like 5 - 10 feet at the most. For this run
	the wires must be able to handle to full power your inverter
	puts out. So if you have a 4000 watt inverter, your wires need
	to handle that. There is special cable made by Trace and
	others for this (#0 awg, at $5/foot) which being
	multi-stranded, is easier to work with. Other folks use
	welding wire even though it isn't specified by the NEC code
	because it has the same performance at high voltage, and it's
	much cheaper.
      </para>

      <para>
	The battery interconnects also need to be rather large, since
	they also have to handle large voltages. Most battery
	companies will supply with a set of interconnects if you buy
	more than 6 batteries. Otherwise you can buy them from a
	number of soalr energy suppliers, or make your own. Most do it
	yourself types are made using copper tubing, hammered flat on
	one end with a hole drilled in it, and the other end swagged,
	crimped, soldered, or welded to the end.
      </para>

      <para>
	The panels themselves can usually be wired with standard 10
	awg or 12 awg wire between them. The connections into the
	junction box needs to be water proof, and caulking just
	doesn't quite cut it... I've seen more than a few systems have
	problems when water got in and fried something. I prefer using
	3 conductor tray cable, which is properly rated for outside
	use, and being round, watertight connectors are easier to
	find.
      </para>

      <para>
	A charge controller is needed between the PV array, and the
	batteries. This will need to be 12, 24, or 48 volts, depending
	on your system. Some charge controllers will take 48VDC, and
	output 12VDC or 24VDC, which is great if you have a long wire
	run between your array and the batteries.
      </para>


    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="howpower">
      <title>The Power Distribution Center</title>

      <para>
	The distribution center is where all the wires come together,
	and then go out again to the rest of the house. The first
	component is the main shutoff switch, which is typically 250
	amps. This is between the batteries and everything else, and
	shuts down *everything*.
      </para>

      <para>
	From there, the 24VDC goes to the house, and to the
	inverter. It is also possible to add an equalizer to get 12VDC
	from a 24VDC system. Ideally theer are also cutoffs using 60
	amp breakers for the 12 and 24VDC sub systems. It is perfectly
	fine to have a series of disconnects using 15 amp breakers to
	give you fine tuning of what can be shut off for maintainance
	purposes. I personally have a main disconnect on every sub
	system, and then the 120VAC, 12VDC, and 24VDC subsystems all
	go to breaker boxes where they get further sub divided for
	lights, pumps, fridge, fans, etc...
      </para>

      <para>
	While you can build up your own power center from parts, it's
	a bit more work, and potentially more expensive than buying a
	pre-manufactured power center. Both Outback and Trace build
	power centers, all prewired for their inverters, charge
	controllers, and other components. My own system, which was
	built by canabalizing the old system, and splicing in new
	components, is probably more work than most folsk want to deal
	with.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="howbatteries">
      <title>The Battery Bank</title>

      <para>
	Most batteries for off-grid houses are 6VDC, or 2VDC. A few
	are 12VDC, but this isn't very common. Most of the old
	telephone company, or old missle silo batteries with a 50 year
	life span, are 2VDC.
      </para>

      <para>
	There are several types of batteries, but what it all comes
	down to is how many years life can you expect. Longer lasting
	batteries cost more, but may last 15 - 20 years. Cheaper
	batteries cost less, but then you have to replace them every
	5-7 years.
      </para>

      <para>
	There is also the issue of size. To get the same amount of
	power, you can have many little batteries, or a few big
	ones. While the many small ones may be cheaper initially, the
	wiring can be a nightmare. Usually batter banks with over 16
	batteries should be wired with solid bars, rather than
	wire. So using fewer big batteries, you can reduce the wiring
	hassle to some thing more manageable.
      </para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ============= My System ============================== -->
  <sect1 id="mysystem"> 
    <title>My Hybrid System</title>

    <para>
      For an example, I'll document my own power system, which
      I've spent the last few years upgrading to a more state of the
      art system. My double geodesic domes were originally built in
      1980, and for that time, it was a pretty standard design. How
      times change... 
    </para>

    <sect2 id="photovoltaics">
      <title>Photovoltaics</title>

      <para>
	For a long time we've limped by on the 20 year old
	photovoltaic panels that were there when I bought my
	house. These panels comprised of 8 Arco 16-2000 panels (rated
	at 35 watts), and 2 Solec Panels (rated at 90 watts) for a
	grand total of 460 (if running at full efficiency) watts. This
	isn't much when compared with other fully off-grid houses. We've
	managed by being heavily propane dependant. I recently
	installed 16 Evergreen EC-110 panels to reduce my propane
	dependancy, and switch to more DC devices.
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/newpv.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>

      <para>
	Upgrading the photovoltaic array turned out to be more of a
	carpentry and ditch digging project than an electrical one. I
	was working on a 45 degree roof, too steep to stand on, and
	impossible to get a ladder on. So I was forced to hanging in a
	climbing harness off of a few climbing bolts I put in. Once I
	got a few of the footers installed through the wood shake roof,
	I could then use those for foot rests, tie off points, or
	directional anchors. It did make things a bit slow though,
	plus working on flashing and reshingling parts of a wood roof
	are a major pain in the neck.
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/barerack.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>

      <para>
	When it comes to working on a wood shake roof, you need to buy
	round standoffs to use instead of the feet that come with the
	rack. These ate the size of plumbing vent pipes, so you can
	use standard vent pipe flashing to keep your roof from
	leaking. I also sealed all the bolt holes with caulk, and
	tarred the flashing into place.
      </para>

      <para>
	The slowest part was probably digging the 130 foot trench deep
	enough. Here in the Colorado Rockies, ditch digging should be
	an olympic sport. Rather than go through the house, entailing
	lots of conduit work, and digging some how under my deck
	without destroying it, I went around the house from the garage
	(where the new panels are now) to the power shed. About a quarter
	of the trench was through previous excavated dirt around the
	septic tank, so digging through that wasn't hard at all. But
	the other half involved drilling rocks, and lots of sledge
	hammering. Good exercise, but really slow.
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/abelditch.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>

    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="windgenerators">
      <title>Wind Generators</title>

      <para>
	When I bought this place, it came with an ancient Paris
	Dunn 5kw wind generator that was broken, and a small
	WhisperLight 430 that soon after I bought this house. I
	recently installed a recording wind meter on my tower, and the
	data has been good. At least during this dark time of the
	fall, we get less than 3 hours of sunlight, but the wind has
	been blowing about 30mph steadily for weeks! So this summer I
	plan to install a new Bergey XL-1 1000 Watt wind generator.
      </para>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="images/tower.png" format="png"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="control">
      <title>Power Center</title>

      <para>
	My old power system was a joke of homebuilt and ancient
	electronics. For one thing, it only had a single disconnect
	for everything, including all the DC and AC circuits. After we
	suffered through a major crash because of the lack of
	electrical isolation, I decided to redesign it all. The
	spontaneously fried Heart inverter was replaced with a Trace
	4024 Inverter, and I added all the disconnects required by the
	NEC code, as well as a few more for ease of maintainance.
      </para>

      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject>
	  <imagedata fileref="images/rewire01.png" format="png"/>
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      
      <para>
	The rewiring project of the power center started well, but
	at this altitude, the weather can change quick. It went from a 
	reasonably warm spring day, to a windy cold one. It took about
	3 days, but I replaced everything, brought it up to code, and
	left room for future expansion as well. It was a bit of a
	canabalizing project mixed with redesigning, reusing
	components, and adding more disconnects and a new charge
	controller.
      </para>

    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="Batteries">
      <title>Batteries</title>

      <para>
	When I bought this place, it came with 12 Trojan L16
	batteries that were about 7 years old. (a little past
	warrenty). These died a year or so later due to age. I
	replaced them with a 8 Surette 6CS-25PS batteries (roughly 3
	times the storage capacity) I have heard stories the original
	owners used dozens of car batteries for power.
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/batt01.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>

      <para>
	I've got neighbors with amazingly small systems. My closest
	neighbor (over the hill) runs on 16 golf cart batteries.
	Another neighbor ran on 4. It's doable if you don't mind
	running a backup generator alot, but I prefer sufficient
	backup storage.
      </para> 

    </sect2> 

    <sect2 id="backup">
      <title>Backup Generator</title>

      <para>
	I have a Honda 5000 watt generator that puts out both 120VAC,
	as well as 240VAC. This is mostly used to run the 240VAC deep
	well pump. I soon plan to replace that pump with a DC
	one. This generator has been modified to run on propane, which
	is much nicer in cold or bad weather than dealing with fuel
	cans. It does suck quite a bit of propane however.
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/abelgen.png" format="png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </para>

      <para>
	One day, while I was filling the cistern, the generator caught
	on fire. If I hadn't been around and had a working fire
	extinqusher handy, it might have been a disaster. This is one
	good reason to never have an automatic startup switch for your
	generator. This day it was particularly stressful, as I was
	filling the cistern because there was a large forest fire 2-3
	miles away.
      </para> 

    </sect2> 

  </sect1>

  <!-- ============= NEC Compliance ============================== -->
  <sect1 id="neccomply"> 
    <title>The NEC and You</title>

    <para>
      The National Electrical Code was developed by, and is still
      maintained by the National Fire Protection Association
      (NFPA). A number of years ago the code was updated for
      photovoltaic and wind power systems based on research done at
      <ulink type="http" url="http://www.re.sandia.gov">Sandia
      National Labs</ulink> in New Mexico.
    </para>

    <para>
      A good start on understanding the NEC code is 
      <ulink type="http"
	     url="http://www.senecass.com/NEC2000.pdf">this
      document</ulink> called "Photovoltaic Power Systems and the
      National Code". It was written by John Wiles, one of the main
      researchers at Sandia, and is an expanded version of the
      section of the code that deals with photovoltaic systems. The
      basic idea of the NEC code is to avoid fires, and other
      associated problems caused by insufficient wiring.
    </para>

    <para>
      The NEC code document itself costs about $65, and is available
      from the <ulink type="http" url="http://www.nfpa.org">National
      Fire Protection Association</ulink>. Although the actual code
      as published needs to the one you should use for all design
      decisions, <ulink type="http"
      url="http://www.senecass.com/NEC-code-draft.pdf">here is a
      copy of a rough draft</ulink> of the code that can give you an
      idea what the NEC actually looks like. Warning, this is a big
      document.
    </para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ============= Resources ============================== -->
  <sect1 id="resources"> 
    <title>Other Resources</title>
    
    <sect2 id="Literature">
      <title>Literature</title>
      <para>
	<ulink type="http" url="http://www.homepower.com">Home Power
	Magazine</ulink>, of course. My favorite source of
	inspiration.
      </para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="supplies">
      <title>Sources of Supplies</title>
      <para>
	<ulink type="http" url="http://www.realgoods.com">Real
	Goods</ulink> is the largest, and one of the oldest renewable
	suppliers around. A few years ago they merged with my local
	supplier, Jade Mountain.
      </para>
      
      <para>
	<ulink type="http" url="http://www.outbackpower.com/">Outback
	Power Systems</ulink> makes inverters and other power system
	components. I use their MX60 60 Amp charge controller because
	it takes 48 VDC input, and puts out 24VDC.
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http"
	       url="http://www.traceengineering.com">Trace
	Engineering</ulink> has been the standard in inverters for
	many years.
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http" url="http://www.rvpowerproducts.com">RV
	Products</ulink> makes charge controllers.
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http"
	       url="http://www.bergey.com/">Bergey</ulink> makes the best and
	most reliable wind generators.
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http" url="http://www.worldpowertech.com">World
	Power Technologies</ulink> makes the Whisperlight series of
	wind generators.
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http" url="http://www.vanner.com">Vanner Inc.</ulink>
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http"
	       url="http://www.honda-generators.com">Honda Generators</ulink>
	Other than cars, Honda is know for it's generators.
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http"
	       url="http://www.telemobile.com">Telemobile</ulink> makes
	dedicated wireless phone systems that are good enough to
	support a dial up modem connection.I have a Ptel system
	installed.
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http"
	       url="http://www.rollsbattery.com">Rolls/Surette
	Batteries</ulink> Rolls Battery makes large household sized
	batteries with a ling lifespan and easy maintainance.
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http"
	       url="http://www.trojan-battery.com">Trojan Battery</ulink>
	makes batteries that have long been the standard for off-grid
	houses.
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http"
	       url="http://www.dankoffsolar.com/">Dankoff </ulink> imports
	several different types of water pumps for all sizes and
	budgets.
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http"
	       url="http://www.evergreensolar.com/">Evergreen Solar</ulink>
	makes photovoltaic panels in a very different way which is
	more environmentally friendly than most manufacturers.
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http"
	       url="http://www.unirac.com/">Uni-Rac</ulink> makes really nice
	racks for mounting solar panels too. I've also built my owm
	racks out of wood or metal, but the Uni-Rac's made this
	project much easier and were worth the money.
      </para>

      <para>
	<ulink type="http"
	       url="http://www.sunfrost.com/">SunFrost</ulink> makes very
	energy efficient DC freezers and refridgeraters.
      </para>


    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="other">
      <title>Web Sites</title>

      <para>
	
      </para>

    </sect2>
    
  </sect1>


  <!-- ============= Authors ================================ -->

  <sect1 id="authors">
    <title>Authors</title>
    <para>
      <application>GNUae</application> was written by Rob Savoye
      (<email>rob@senecass.com</email>).  Please send all comments,
      suggestions, and bug reports to <email>rob@senecass.com</email>
    </para>

  </sect1>


  <!-- ============= Application License ============================= -->
  
  <sect1 id="license">
    <title>License</title>
    <para>
      This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
      modify it under the terms of the <citetitle>GNU General Public
      License</citetitle> as published by the Free Software Foundation;
      either version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later
      version.
    </para>
    <para>
      This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
      WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
      MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
      <citetitle>GNU General Public License</citetitle> for more details.
    </para>
    <para>
      A copy of the <citetitle>GNU General Public License</citetitle> is
      included as an appendix to the <citetitle>GNOME Users
      Guide</citetitle>.  You may also obtain a copy of the
      <citetitle>GNU General Public License</citetitle> from the Free
      Software Foundation by visiting <ulink type="http"
      url="http://www.fsf.org">their Web site</ulink> or by writing to
      <address>
	Free Software Foundation, Inc.
	<street>59 Temple Place</street> - Suite 330
	<city>Boston</city>, <state>MA</state> <postcode>02111-1307</postcode>
	<country>USA</country>
      </address>
    </para>
  </sect1>
</article>
